part 2 chapter 8.
They had done it, they had done it at last!
The room that we're standing in was long shaped and softly lit.
The telescreen was dimmed to a low murmur; the richness of the dark blue
carpet gave one the impression of trading on velvet.
At the far end of the room O'Brien was sitting at a table under a green shaded
lamp, with a massive papers on either side of him.
He had not bothered to look up when the servant showed Julia and Winston in.
Winston's heart was thumping so hard that he doubted whether he would be able to speak.
They had done it, they had done it at last, was all he could think.
It had been a rash act to come here at all, and sheer folly to arrive together;
though it was true that they had come by different routes and only met on O'Brien's doorstep.
But merely to walk into such a place needed an effort of the nerve.
It was only on very rare occasions that one saw inside the Dwelling Places of
the Inner Party, or even penetrated into the quarter of the town where they lived.
The whole atmosphere of the huge block of flats, the richness and spaciousness
of everything, the unfamiliar smells of good food and good tobacco, the silent
and incredibly rapid lifts sliding up and down, the white jacketed servants
hurrying to and fro— —everything was intimidating.
Although he had a good pretext for coming here, he was haunted at every step
by the fear that a black uniformed God would suddenly appear from around the
corner, demand his papers and order him to get out.
O'Brien's servant, however, had admitted the two of them without demur.
He was a small, dark-haired man in a white jacket, with a diamond shaped
completely expressionless face which might have been that of a Chinese.
The passage down which he led them was softly carpeted, with cream papered walls
and white wainscoting, all exquisitely clean.
That too was intimidating. Winston could not remember ever to have seen a
passageway whose walls were not grimy from the contact of human bodies.
O'Brien had a slip of paper between his fingers and seemed to be studying it intently.
His heavy face, bent down so that one could see the line of the nose, looked
both formidable and intelligent.
For perhaps 20 seconds he sat without stirring.
Then he pulled the speak right towards him and wrapped out a message in the
hybrid jargon of the Ministries: Items one comma 5 comma 7 approved
full-wise stop suggestion contained item 6 double plus ridiculous virgin crime
think canceled stop and proceed construction-wise anti-getting plus full estimates
machinery overhead stop end message.
He rose deliberately from his chair and came towards them across the soundless carpet.
A little of the official atmosphere seemed to have fallen away from him with
the new speak words, but his expression was grimmer than usual, as though he were
not pleased at being disturbed.
The terror that Winston already felt was suddenly shot through by a streak of
ordinary embarrassment.
It seems to him quite possible that he had simply made a stupid mistake. For
what evidence had he in reality that O'Brien was any kind of political
conspirator? Nothing but a flash of the eyes and a single equivocal remark:
beyond that, only his own secret imaginings, founded on a dream.
He could not even fall back on the pretense that he had come to borrow the
Dictionary, because in that case Julia's presence was impossible to explain.
As O'Brien passed the tele screener thoughts seemed to strike him.
He stopped, turned aside and pressed a switch on the wall. There was a sharp snap.
The voice had stopped.
Julia uttered a tiny sound, a sort of squeak of surprise.
Even in the midst of Hispanic Winston was too much taken aback to be able to
hold his tongue.
'You can turn it off!' he said.
'Yes,' said O'Brien, 'we can turn it off. We have that privilege.'
He was opposite them now. His solid form towered over the pair of them, and the
expression on his face was still indecipherable.
He was waiting, somewhat sternly, for Winston to speak, but about what?
Even now it was quite conceivable that he was simply a busy man wondering
irritably why he had been interrupted.
Nobody spoke.
After the stopping of the telescreen the room seemed deadly silent.
The seconds marched past, enormous.
With difficulty Winston continued to keep his eyes fixed on her brands
and suddenly the grim face broke down into what might have been the beginnings of a smile.
With his characteristic gesture a brand resettled his spectacles on his nose.
'Shall I say it, or will you?' he said.
'I will say it,' said Winston promptly the thing is really turned off?'
'Yes, everything is turned off. We are alone.'
'We have come here because— He paused realizing for the first time
the vagueness of his own motives. Since he did not in fact know what kind of
help he expected from her Brian it was not easy to say why he had come here.
He went on, conscious that what he was saying must sound both feeble and pretentious:
'We believe that there is some kind of conspiracy, some kind of secret
organization working against the Party, and that you were involved in it.
We want to join it and work for it. We are enemies of the Party.
We just believe in the principles of insock We are thought criminals We are also adulterers.
I tell you this because we want to put ourselves at your mercy.
If you want us to incriminate ourselves in any other way, we are ready.'
He stopped and glanced over his shoulder, with the feeling that the door had opened.
Sure enough, the little yellow-faced servant had come in without knocking.
Winston saw that he was carrying a tree with a decanter and glasses.
'Martin is one of us,' said O'Brien impassively. 'Bring the drinks over here,
Martin. Put them on the round table.
Have we enough chairs? Then we may as well sit down and talk in comfort.
Bring a chair for yourself, Martin. This is business. You can stop being a servant
for the next 10 minutes.'
The little man sat down quiet at his ease, and yet still with a servant like
air, the heir of a valley enjoying a privilege.
Winston regarded him out of the corner of his eye.
It struck him that the man's whole life was playing a part, and that he felt it
to be dangerous to drop his assumed personality even for a moment
LeBron took the decanter by the neck and filled up the glasses with a dark red
liquid. It aroused in Winston dim memories of something seen long ago on a wall or a hoarding—
—a vast bottle composed of electric lights which seemed to move up and down
and pour its contents into a glass.
Seen from the top the stuff looked almost black, but in the Decatur it
gleamed like a ruby. It had a sour sweet smell.
He saw Julia pick up her glass and sniff at it with frank curiosity.
'It is called wine,' said O'Brien with a faint smile. 'You will have read about it
in books, no doubt. Not much of it gets to the Outer Party I'm afraid.'
His face grew solemn again, and he raised his glass: 'I think it is fitting that we should
begin by drinking a health.
To our Leader: To Emmanuel Goldstein.'
Winston took up his glass with a certain eagerness.
Wine was a thing he had read and dreamed about.
Like the glass paperweight or Mr cherrington's half-remembered rhymes, it
belonged to the vanished, romantic past, the olden time as he likes to call it in
his secret thoughts.
For some reason he had always thought of wine as having an intensely sweet taste,
like that of blackberry jam, and an immediate intoxicating effect.
Actually, when he came to swallow it, the stuff was distinctly disappointing. The
truth was that after years of gin drinking he could barely taste it.
He sat down the empty glass.
'Then there is such a person as Goldstein?'
he said.
'Yes, there is such a person, and he is alive. Where, I do not know.'
'And the conspiracy— —the organization is It real is it not simply an invention
of the Thought Police?'
'No, it is real. The Brotherhood, we call it.
You will never learn much more about the Brotherhood than that it exists and that
you belong to it.
I will come back to that presently.'
He looked at his wrist watch It is unwise even for members of the
Inner Party to turn off the telescreen for more than half an hour.
You ought not to have come here together, and you will have to leave separately.
You, Comrade'— '—he bowed his head to Julia—' —'will leave first.
We have about 20 minutes at our disposal.
You will understand that I must start by asking you certain questions.
In general terms, what are you prepared to do?'
'Anything that we are capable of,' said Winston her brand had turned himself a little in
his chair so that he was facing Winston.
He almost ignored Julia, seeming to take it for granted that Winston could speak
for her. For a moment the lids flitted down over his eyes.
He began asking his questions in a low, expressionless voice, as though this were
a routine, a sort of catechism, most of whose answers were known to him already.
'You were prepared to give your lives?' 'Yes.'
'You were prepared to commit murder?'
'Yes.' 'To commit acts of sabotage which may cause the death of hundreds of innocent people?'
'Yes.'
'To betray your country to foreign powers?'
'You were prepared to cheat, to forge, to blackmail, to corrupt the minds of
children, to distribute habit-forming drugs, to encourage prostitution, to
disseminate venereal diseases— —to do anything which is likely to cause
demoralization and weaken the power of the Party?'
'Yes.'
'If, for example, it would somehow serve our interests to throw sulfuric acid in
a child's face— —are you prepared to do that?'
'Yes.'
'You are prepared to lose your identity and live out the rest of your life as a
waiter or a dock worker Yes.'
'You are prepared to commit suicide, if and when we order you to do so?'
'Yes.'
'You are prepared, the two of you, to separate and never see one another again?'
'No broken Julia.
It appeared to Winston that a long time passed before he answered. For a moment
he seemed even to have been deprived of the power of speech.
His tongue worked soundlessly, forming the opening syllables first of one word,
then of the other, over and over again.
Until he had said it, he did not know which word he was going to say.
'No,' he said finally.
'You did well to tell me,' said O'Brien. 'It is necessary for us to know everything.'
He turned himself toward Julia and added in a voice with somewhat more expression in it:
'Do you understand that even if he survives, it maybe as a different person?
We may be obliged to give him a new identity.
His face, his movements, the shape of his hands, the color of his hair— —even his
voice would be different.
And you yourself might have become a different person.
Our surgeons can alter people beyond recognition. Sometimes it is necessary.
Sometimes we even amputate a limb.'
Winston could not help snatching another side long glance at Martin's Mongolian face.
There were no scars that he could see.
Julia had turned a shade paler, so that her freckles were showing, but she faced
her brand boldly.
She murmured something that seemed to be a scent Good and that is settled.'
There was a silver box of cigarettes on the table. With a rather absent bounded
air O'Brien pushed them towards the others, took one himself, then stood up
and began to pace slowly to and fro, as though he could think better standing.
They were very good cigarettes, very thick and well packed with an unfamiliar
silkiness in the paper.
O'Brien looked at his wristwatch again.
'You had better go back to your pantry, Martin,' he said. 'I shall switch on in a
quarter of an hour. Take a good look at these comrades' faces before you go. You
will be seeing them again. I may not.'
Exactly as they had done at the front door, the little man's dark eyes
flickered over their faces.
There was not a trace of fringiness in his manner.
He was memorizing their appearance, but he felt no interest in them, or appeared to feel none.
It occurred to Winston that a synthetic face was perhaps incapable of changing its expression.
Without speaking or giving any kind of salutation, Martin went out, closing the
door silently behind him.
O'Brien was strolling up and down, one hand in the pocket of his black overalls,
the other holding his cigarette.
'You understand,' he said, 'that you will be fighting in the dark. You will always be
in the dark.
You will receive orders and you will obey them, without knowing why.
Later I shall send you a book from which you will learn the true nature of the
society we live in, and the strategy by which we shall destroy it.
When you have read the book, you will be full members of the Brotherhood.
But between the general aims that we are fighting for, and the immediate tasks of
the moment, you will never know anything.
I tell you that the Brotherhood exists, but I cannot tell you whether it numbers
100 members, or 10 million.
From your personal knowledge you will never be able to say that it numbers
even as many as it doesn't You will have three or four contacts, who
will be renewed from time to time as they disappear.
As this was your first contact, it will be preserved.
When you receive orders, they will come from me.
If we find it necessary to communicate with you, it will be through Martin.
When you are finally caught, you will confess. That is unavoidable. But you will
have very little to confess, other than your own actions.
You will not be able to betray more than a handful of unimportant people.
Probably you will not even betray me.
By that time I may be dead, or I shall have become a different person, with a
different face.'
He continued to move to and fro over the soft carpet. In spite of the bulkiness of
his body there was a remarkable grace in his movements. It came out even in the
gesture with which he thrust a hand into his pocket, or manipulated a cigarette.
More even than of strength, he gave an impression of confidence and of an
understanding tinted by irony.
However much he known as he might be, he had nothing of the single-mindedness
that belongs to a fanatic.
When he spoke of murder, suicide, venereal disease, amputated limbs and altered
faces, it was with a faint air of perciflage This is unavoidable,' his voice seemed to
say; 'this is what we have got to do, unflinchingly. But this is not what we
shall be doing when life is worth living again.'
A wave of admiration, almost of worship, flowed out from Winston towards O'Brien.
For the moment he had forgotten the shadowy figure of Goldstein.
When you looked at O'Brien's powerful shoulders and his blunt featured face, so
ugly and yet so civilized it was impossible to believe that he could be defeated.
There was no stratagem that he was not equal to, no danger that he could not foresee.
Even Julia seemed to be impressed. She had let her cigarette go out and was
listening intently her Brian went on: 'You will have heard rumors of the
existence of the Brotherhood now that you have formed your own picture of it.
You have imagined, probably, a huge underworld of conspirators, meeting
secretly in sellers scribbling messages on walls recognizing one another by code
words or by special movements of the hand.
Nothing of the kind exists.
The members of the Brotherhood have no way of recognizing one another, and it is
impossible for any one member to be aware of the identity of more than a few others.
Goldstein himself, if he fell into the hands of the Thought Police, could not
give them a complete list of members, or any information that would lead them to
a complete list.
No such list exists.
The Brotherhood cannot be wiped out because it is not an organization in the
ordinary sense. Nothing holds it together except an idea which is indestructible.
You will never have anything to sustain you accept the idea you'll get no comradeship and no
encouragement.
When finally your court you will get no help. We never help our members.
At most, when it is absolutely necessary that someone should be silenced, we are
occasionally able to smuggle a razor blade into a prisoner's cell
you'll have to get used to living without results and without hope.
You will work for a while, you will be caught, you will confess, and then you will die.
Those are the only results that you will ever see. There is no possibility that
any perceptible change will happen within our own lifetime.
We are the dead.
Our only true life is in the future.
We shall take part in it as handfuls of dust and splinters of bone.
But how far away that future may be, there is no knowing. It might be a thousand years.
At present nothing is possible except to extend the area of sanity little by little.
We cannot act collectively. We can only spread our knowledge outwards from
individual to individual, generation after generation.
In the face of the thoughts Police, there is no other way.'
He halted and looked for the third time at his wristwatch.
'It is almost time for you to leave, comrade,' he said to Julia. 'Wait. The
decanter is still half full.'
He filled the glasses and raised his own glass by the stem. 'What shall it be this
time?' he said, still with the same fancy suggestion of irony.
'To the confusion of the thoughts Police?
To the death of Big Brother? To humanity?
To the future?'
'To the past,' said Winston.
'The past is more important to Greed O'Brien gravely.
They emptied their glasses, and a moment later Julia stood up to go.
O'Brien took a small box from the top of a cabinet and handed her a flat white
tablet which he told her to place on her tongue.
It was important, he said, not to go out smelling of wine: the lift attendants
were very observant. As soon as the door had shut behind her he appeared to
forget her existence.
He took another pace or two up and down and then stopped.
'There are details to be settled,' he said assume that you have a hiding place of some kind?'
Winston explained about the rumor for Mr cherrington shop.
'That will do for the moment. Later we will arrange something else for you. It
is important to change one's Hiding Place frequently.
Meanwhile I shall send you a copy of the book'' —even O'Brien, Winston noticed, seemed
to pronounce the words as though they were in italics—'
—'Goldstein's book, you understand, as soon as possible.
It may be some days before I can get hold of one. There are not many in
existence, as you can imagine. The Thought Police hunt them down and Destroy them
almost as fast as we can produce them. It makes very little difference. The book is
indestructible.
If the last copy were gone, we could reproduce it almost word for word.
Do you carry a briefcase to work with you?' he added.
'As a rule, yes.'
'What is it like?'
'Black, very shabby. With two straps.'
'Black, two straps, very shabby— —good.
One day in the fairly near future— —I cannot give a date— —one of the messages
among your morning's work will contain a misprinted word, and you will have to ask for a repeat.
On the following day you will go to work without your briefcase
At some time during the day, in the street, a man will touch you on the arm
and say, "I think you have dropped your briefcase." The one he gives you will
contain a copy of Goldstein's book. You will return it within 14 days.'
They were silent for a moment. 'There are a couple of minutes before you need to
go,' said O'Brien. 'We shall meet again— —if we do meet again———' Winston looked up at him.
'In the place where there is no darkness?'
he said hesitantly a brand nodded without appearance of surprise.
'In the place where there is no darkness,' he said, as though he had recognized the illusion
And in the meantime, is there anything that you wish to say before you leave?
Any message? Any question?'
Winston thought.
There did not seem to be any further questions that he wanted to ask: still
this did he feel any impulse to what a high sounding generalities.
Instead of anything directly connected with O'Brien or the Brotherhood that
came into his mind a sort of composite picture of the dark bedroom where his
mother had spent her last days, and the little room over Mr charrington
shop, and the glass paperweight, and the steel engraving in its rosewood frame.
Almost at random he said: 'Did you ever happen to hear an old rhyme
that begins "'Oranges and lemons,' say the bells and Clemens
Again O'Brien nodded. With a sort of grave courtesy he completed the stanza:
'Oranges and lemons,' say the bells of Saint Clements You owe me three
farthings,' say the bells of Saint Martins When will you pay me?' say the bells of older Bailey,
'When I grow rich,' say the bells of Shoreditch.
'You knew the last line!' said Winston.
'Yes, I knew the last line. And now, I am
afraid, it is time for you to go. But wait.
You had better let me give you one of these tablets.'
As Winston stood up her Brian held out a hand. His powerful grip crushed the bones
of Winston's palm.
At the door Winston looked back, but O'Brien seemed already to be in the
process of putting him out of mind.
He was waiting with his hand on the switch that controlled the telescreen.
Beyond him Winston could see the writing table with its green shaded lamp and the
speak right and the wire baskets deep Laden with papers.
The incident was closed.
Within 30 seconds, it occurred to him a brand would be back at his interrupted
and important work on behalf of the Party